<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of the birth and burning of the image called St. Michael, or, A new letter to Mr. Jonathan Saunders, lecturer of All-Saints-Barking being the answer of Mr. Edmund Sherman, late church-warder to a sham libel (without any authors name) called The sham-indictment quashed ...</title>
            <author>Sherman, Edmund, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59913</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28864</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10771963</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10771963</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45777</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59913)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45777)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1410:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of the birth and burning of the image called St. Michael, or, A new letter to Mr. Jonathan Saunders, lecturer of All-Saints-Barking being the answer of Mr. Edmund Sherman, late church-warder to a sham libel (without any authors name) called The sham-indictment quashed ...</title>
                  <author>Sherman, Edmund, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mr. Sherman and published by Richard Janeway,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45777:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE Birth and Burning OF THE IMAGE CALLED St. MICHAEL: OR A New Letter to Mr. <hi>Jonathan Saunders</hi> Lecturer of <hi>All-Saints-Barking.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">BEING The Anſwer of Mr. <hi>Edmund Sherman</hi> Late Church-Warden, to a Sham Libel (without any Authors Name) called, <hi>The Sham-Indictment Quaſht;</hi> which begins with this Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Where no Law is, there is no Tranſgreſſion;</hi> And endeth with this Text, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 4.5. <hi>The Unjuſt knoweth no Shame.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>My Anſwer to this Dark Lanthorn Nameleſs Author ſhall begin with this Text; <hi>Men Love Darkneſs rather than Light, becauſe their Deeds are evil,</hi> Joh. 3.19. and conclude with another Text, as the Lecturer doth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. <hi>Jonathan Saunders,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SIR, Meeting with another vagrant Brat, Chriſtned the <hi>Sham Indictment Quaſht,</hi> and you having already appeared in Print, to be the Father of two Brats Chriſtned (as ſuppoſed by my laſt, without Canonical Goſſips) by the fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Names called <hi>Apparitions;</hi> both then treating upon the ſame Subject, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you have Learnedly wrot in defence of St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s <hi>Image:</hi> Taking then for Text, <hi>Thou that abhorreſt Idols, doſt thou commit Sacriledge:</hi> I have reaſon to Charge you with a Suſpicion at leaſt of being Father of this By-blow alſo; which you In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45777:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>to Nurſe up with ſuch Milk as can be drawn from the Breaſts of thoſe proper Texts.</p>
            <p>I confeſs it's ſomewhat an unequal Match for me that am but a <hi>Lay-man</hi> to grapple with a <hi>Clergy-man;</hi> who are both a <hi>Countrey Viccar</hi> and a <hi>City Lecturer;</hi> For I have ſomewhere that Saint Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> (whoſe Books I doubt not but you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may be acquainted with) Interpreting that place of <hi>Job; The Oxen Plowed, and the Aſſes fed by them:</hi> He opens the Text thus; that by <hi>Oxen</hi> were Allegorically meant the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and by <hi>Aſſes</hi> the <hi>Laity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Aſſes</hi> indeed <hi>Jonathan</hi> you would make of us, more particularly me: If I muſt do Pennance in three lewd Sheets ſucceſſively in print, for medling with your Images, without daring to reply: However, there was once an Aſs that luckily <hi>Reprov'd the Madneſs</hi> of a pretended <hi>Prophet,</hi> and therefore I ſhall run the venture, and tell you my mind freely, as I am wont to talk in ſuch home-ſpun Language as may be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſuch a ſorry Quondam Church-Warden as you have expoſed me to be.</p>
            <p>This laſt Pamphlet, called <hi>The Sham-Indictment Quaſht,</hi> is a kind of Triumph for your Victry, becauſe forſooth the Indictment (but why the Sham-Indictment) as to the Doctor and your ſelf was quaſht; but what I pray was the true Reaſon?</p>
            <p>Why; When a Pariſh that hath been Indicted for letting ſome offenſive and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſtinking Carrion, or other Rubbiſh, lye in the Kings High-way, ſhall come and plead by Learned Council, and the Doctor of the Pariſh vouching the truth, that the Nuſance for which the Indictment was brought, is Removed, Buried or Burnt, is it not eaſie and of courſe to get the Indictment quaſht? So in this Caſe, where for the ſtanding and being of a great Carved, Guilded Image, Called St. <hi>Michael,</hi> upon the Commandments of God, and in a Proteſtant Church; the Church-Wardens, Doctor, and Lecturer, having been all Indicted for it, and the ſame being in it ſelf Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and an offence, and ſo Indictable at Common Law (as ſome in Court told the Doctor;) But yet upon the Doctors ſpeaking, (and whatever he ſayes is <hi>Verbum Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotis,</hi>) and pleading by Learned Council alſo that the Image for which the Indictment was brought, is taken down and Burnt, and ſo the offence ceaſed, there was with the leſs trouble obtained a Quaſh to the Indictment againſt the Doctor and Lecturers part, though it coſt them a Traverſe and two Seſſions Charges to get off by way of Defence of an <hi>Image;</hi> whereas the Church-Wardens by ſubmitting got off with leſs Charge and trouble at firſt Seſſions; and I am ſtill of opinion that my Burning was much more commendable than your defending the Image. And therefore very filly is this great boaſting in print, of a brave Conqueſt the Doctor and Lecturer have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in quaſhing the Indictment, and yet are aſhamed to publiſh your Name to vouch the Print.</p>
            <p>You ſay the Proſecutor (which was Mr. <hi>Whitaker</hi>) did not appear: No I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you, for the ſtinking Carrion being gone and Burnt, and ſo the Offence and Scandal taken away, he was wiſer than to ſpend a penny of Money more to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you, which makes men think the Man had no Malice.</p>
            <p>But ſtill this Pamphlet ſhews that you make as much uſe as you can of your old Plea, <hi>viz. That it had not the ſhape of St.</hi> Michael, <hi>nor was ever Reputed the Image of that or any other Saint:</hi> Well, what then? yet it was an Image, and ſuch an Image as did give great Offence and Scandal, eſpecially ſtanding in ſuch a place; and have not all true Proteſtants Reaſon to be angry with you, for chooſing ſuch a Text as this upon the Victory, <hi>viz. Where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion?</hi> Let all true prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants Bluſh, to ſee one who bore the Name of a proteſtant Lecturer, Trump up ſuch a Text on ſo laudable occaſion as in defence of an Image, and at ſuch a Critical mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute when we ſo much fear Popery; which if that Religion ſhould enter, all the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits and Prieſts of St. <hi>Michael</hi> and other Images, would ſet up St. <hi>Michael,</hi> St. <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and your Friend <hi>Whitebreads</hi> Image, and plead the ſame Text, <hi>Where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion,</hi> and quote and thank our Lecturer for ſtarting ſuch a plea.</p>
            <p>And at the ſame rate any Miniſters that ſhall be popiſhly affected, may take a great ſtring of Beads, and Crucifixes and tumble them over openly in the Church, and uſe many ſuch fooliſh trinkets as may ſuſpiciouſly tend to introduce Popery, and (if Indicted) plead, Where is no Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you ſhall dare to ſay <hi>in verbo Sacerdotis,</hi> that no Clergy-man belonging to this Pariſh of <hi>All-Saints Barkin,</hi> had any hand in this Sham Pamphlet or the other two Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45777:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>or ſaw or heard of them or either of them, before they were Printed, I have ſuch proofs as ſhall make you Bluſh, except you fly to your other Text, <hi>viz. That the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt knoweth no ſhame.</hi> Your very Texts may convince any Man, that this Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet came from the ſame hand, from which the other Pamphlet came which had this Text, <hi>viz. Thou that abhorreſt Idols, doeſt thou commit Sacriledge?</hi> which was a fit Text for our Lecturer to apply, and call the Burning of the <hi>Image</hi> Sacriledge, though the Image was never more conſecrated than any old Broom belonging to the Church. Thus much in anſwer to your own Texts.</p>
            <p>You have not quoted all the Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth. Particularly, you have willfully omitted the Proviſo, which only provides for the ſtanding and remaining of only ſuch Pictures or Images as are on Toombs and Monuments. It is a pretty Plea, fit for Papiſts to ſay, That Law was only for aboliſhing all ſuch Maſs-Books and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as were then ſtanding and being: Yea, but we may ſet them up againſt we new make the Images, and bring in the ſame Maſs-Books if we new print them, and ſo plead theſe are not the ſame that were then ſtanding and being; for this Image was made <hi>Anno</hi> 59. without order of Veſtry, but by the mear Fancy of Mr. <hi>Ben. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> when he was Church-Warden: So then you would make the Fancy of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> the Church-Warden to have outwitted the Law of <hi>Edward</hi> the King. <hi>Ben.</hi> is a true Church-man, and I am ſure a great Enemy to Papiſts, therefore they will never Saint him for the Contrivance, becauſe <hi>Ben</hi>'s Fancy reacht only to put him on the Steeple; it was not he, no I warrant you, that Removed him and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him as an Ornament to the Commandements, by ſtanding on the top of them, as ready to kick the Second Commandement out of doors, as ſoon as ever Popery ſhould enter.</p>
            <p>But then <hi>pag.</hi> 3. you ſeem very skilful in the knowledge of Images and their Names for you tell the World in print, that the top of the Church of <hi>Barkin</hi> is ſet about with Guilded figures called <hi>Seraphims,</hi> and in the firſt Pamphlet <hi>pag.</hi> 2. you tell us the Names of others in our Church, <hi>viz. Saturn, Mars,</hi> and other Pagan Idols: A man would think you had been at the Chriſtning, if not as Lecturer, yet as Clark to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> out of ſpite to the poor Clark, to hinder him of Fees and Gloves: Or elſe perhaps you ſtood Godfather; elſe how ſhouldſt thou come ſo intimate with theſe lofty things?</p>
            <p>As for theſe things you call Seraphims on the very Roof of our Church; they are nothing but meer Faces, with Wings on each ſide of their Chops; and yet canſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently tell us who they are by their very Grinning or Gritting; nay you tell us their very qualities, for thou faieſt they are the higheſt Order of Angels. O the Depth of this Wiſdom! it is learnedly ſaid; becauſe they ſtand on the top of the Church, <hi>Ergo</hi> they are higheſt: This is moſt Lectorical Logick; ever Boy of <hi>Sandon</hi> knows as much, that he that is on the top of the Steeple is the higheſt Lad in the Pariſh.</p>
            <p>But why doſt thou take things thus by Tradition? Thou art a man of great Faith, for no Man will believe thou ever ſaw'ſt Angel or Seraphim but in Apparition; but I won't grapple with you in this diſpute, nor where they commenced when they took ſuch high Degrees, whether at <hi>Oxford</hi> or at St. <hi>Andrews.</hi> I have no skill in any Saint, till they be grown as big as our Lubber St. <hi>Michael;</hi> nor do I think I ſhould know St. <hi>Michael</hi> if I meet him in Apparition, now his Carving and Guilding is all ſinged off.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe Superior things that have only Faces and no Bodies, I call them only by your General Title of Pamphlets, Apparitions, or Shams, or Lecturers Brats, and leave you to Chriſten them with what Name you pleaſe.</p>
            <p>And they being nothing elſe but Face, you have a fair Mark to Sprinkle at; and they will cry no more at your Chriſtning, than St. <hi>Michael</hi> did when I burnt him; if you ſhall ſay I prophane the Order or Service of the holy Sacrament of Baptiſm, ſo did you, when you called St. <hi>Michael</hi> my God-ſon, <hi>Lectoris ad Exemplum;</hi> O let not the Devil rebuke ſin; and let who will vouch for you, that thoſe are Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phims, as you call them, for I will never be God-father again, ſeeing you have ſo vainly and prophanely defiled the name by applying it to an <hi>Image:</hi> for though its true I have heard that <hi>Papiſts</hi> do Chriſten their Images, yet I never heard they had God-fathers before Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> printed it. Thus I only lay open the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Matter, let other Men enlarge upon your Texts, and your Brats, and your Images, and your defence at Seſſions and in print, and your Bowings, and your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45777:3"/>way of performing Ceremonies, and the timing of them, not beginning them till the Plot was Diſcovering, and untill you had got up St. <hi>Michael,</hi> Organs, and <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread</hi>'s Carpet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> expoſed to view in the Front inſtead of our white Linnen, which the Act of Uniformity Injoyns. For ſure it will be neceſſary for ſome of our Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Clergy in this juncture, to oppoſe that Doctrine of Images, which you ſo ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly advance; (for your whole quarrel is becauſe I pulled down an Image:) Let not Papiſts on one hand be encouraged, and hardned in their Idolatries, and Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks on the other hand pretend ſome ground for their Clamours, that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or at leaſt ſome of her <hi>Seraphim</hi> or <hi>Topp-heavy</hi> Sons are warping towards Popery, though it is in truth only a Lecturer, and a few more; ſcarce one of nine thouſand of the Churches in <hi>England</hi> uſe ſuch Ceremonies as we do (Cathedral, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> excepteds.)</p>
            <p>But towards the end of your Anonimous Pamphlet I met this dreadful Charge, <hi>fol.</hi> 3. <hi>That there is one of theſe Faces ſet up at the Eaſt end of the Church, plum over the Communion Table, towards which the late upper Church-warden, as many of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh will teſtifie, hath frequently Bowed without any ſcruple of Conſcience while the figure called St.</hi> Michael <hi>ſtood thereupon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly all this I can deny as ſtiff as ever any Prieſt of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> or any Jeſuit did at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> that I had no hand in this Plot, I am as clear of it as the Child un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born.</p>
            <p>Pray Name your Witneſſes and Time, when and where, to prove that ever I Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any thing ſet up at the Eaſt end of the Church; but your Pamphlet having no Bodies Name to it, I cannot tell who to go to but to you, our Apparition Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer; and if you can't bring Real Corporeal Witneſſes, then bring ſome Apparition to prove it, for I believe thou haſt more Apparitions in thy Budget, <hi>Jonathan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to conclude all this Tragedy, I find at the Rump of this nameleſs Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Pamphlet, there comes out a flaſh like the blaze at the tail of a Comet, with a thundering Sentence or Bull of Condemnation of the Book called, <hi>The Birth and Burning,</hi> &amp;c. Intending, I ſuppoſe to blaſt the Credit thereof, by the ſcribble of one that dares not put his Name to what he prints: But People do the rather run on and buy that Book the more, ſo that it requires a ſecond Impreſſion; becauſe they ſee the Lecturer inclines to Stifle it, but none to Anſwer it: For inſtead of Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any one particular of the Ceremonies charged upon him, to have never except on Communion dayes been performed by him till St. <hi>Michael</hi> was ſet upon the Commandments; this Lecturer does as that Ignorant Author did, who thought the World would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he had fully Confuted the Learned Roman Cardinal, by only ſaying, <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> thou Lyeſt.</p>
            <p>So our <hi>ſine Nomine Pamphleteer,</hi> alias <hi>Lecturer,</hi> or Will in the wiſp, or dark Lanthorn man, or I know not who to call him (becauſe he is aſhamed to print his Name) acts much at the ſame rate, and ſays it was ſome bodies Opinion, that it was a rude, ſcurrilous, inſolent Paper, many falſities therein; but is this all the Anſwer you can give? this is ſtill but <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> thou lyeſt: I tell thee <hi>Johnathan,</hi> it is as true as any thing thou ever ſaidſt or wrote in thy Life of thy own making.</p>
            <p>But who is this Reporter, this Illuſtrious unkown, upon whoſe veracity all this ſtory de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends? <hi>In Nomine omnium ſanctorum,</hi> what art thou, that thus Inviſibly and <hi>ſine Nomine</hi> prints Pamphlets againſt a late Church-warden of <hi>All-ſaints-Barking?</hi> Sure thou art ſome <hi>ubiquitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> ſome Supernumerary Reformado, or ſome hanger on.</p>
            <p>Sir, By your Prieſthood tell me who you are.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Apparition.</speaker>
               <p>I am a thing they call Lecturer, and have got my ſelf in among you, though the Law knows me not, and in former time I have heard the very Name of Lecturer was Branded by ſome high-flying Church men as a tool of Sedition, I mean in 41. But I hope to bring the Name and uſe of Lecturer into Church again with great Benefit, by my great Zeal for Images and Ceremonies, ſhewed in my learned Pamphlets againſt Mr. <hi>Sherman,</hi> for pulling down St. <hi>Michael,</hi> though the times will not yet bare putting my Name to my prints: Pray let me ſtay with this Pariſh till the times may favour Images and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies more, and give me what you pleaſe I'le be content.</p>
               <l>Hark! Hark! Hark!</l>
               <l>A Voyce I hear, but nothing can I ſee;</l>
               <l>Speak, ſpeak, thou griſly Ghoſt what e're thou be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45777:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Aparition.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I am a ſhade, and though no Name I tell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet you ſhall know I lov'd St.</hi> Michael <hi>well.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bring back St.</hi> Michael <hi>to the Altar; then</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I and you'l drink and once be Friends agaen;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elſe with Apparitions you ſhall ever Frighted be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And in your very ſleep St.</hi> Michaels <hi>Ghoſt ſhall ſee.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <p>I muſt Conjure down this Spectrum, and though I am not ſo much a Candidate of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyſhip as to be an Exorciſt or Devil driver; yet I'le try what can be done.</p>
            <p>By the vertue of a late upper Church-Warden of <hi>Omnium Sanctorum,</hi> and in the Name of <hi>Sancta Clara, Sancta Winifred, Sanctus Antonius,</hi> Vaniſh; but more particularly by the all powerfull Name of our great Champion St. <hi>Michael,</hi> I command you down to your ſhades.</p>
            <q>
               <l>This ſaid, away the frightful Mormo flew,</l>
               <l>And Lecturer alone was left in view.</l>
            </q>
            <p>O! was it you, Mr. Apparition Lecturer, that thus frighted me? well, don't print no more Apparitions, and I will ſerve you; do but try me once more, if you can but get me to accept of the Office again, then to pleaſe you, I'le pull that Fa-La-Soll-Clark out of the Desk by the ears, that is ſuch an eye-ſore to thee; I will make him a Desk juſt before you, where he ſhall ſay <hi>Amen</hi> as it were under your feet, that ſo you may Crow over him, and ſo pull down his Pride as I did St. <hi>Michael;</hi> but you muſt not Burn him, leaſt you be Proſecuted for Burning Church Ornaments. For to give the Clark his due, that ſtands at your right hand, he is as good an Ornament as the Lecturer or St. <hi>Michael,</hi> for he keeps us all in tune, (except the Lecturer.) The man ſings well, and does nick a Pſalm as ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the Sermon, as the Lecturer does his Sermon to the occaſion: And pray good Mr. <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition</hi> Lecturer be pacified; and pray preſent my Service to that Divine that Preacht at our Church on Sunday the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>June,</hi> in the Afternoon, who I won't name, becauſe I pay him reſpect: Tell him, I took notice that he made occaſion to inveigh againſt ſuch as Lampoon Miniſters and their Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And tell him I went home and applyed it to my own ſelf as he meant it, and it might have done ſome good upon me; but looking into the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy mens three printed multiplying-Glaſſes, particularly that called a <hi>fiery Apparition, &amp;c.</hi> I ſaw there a Clergy-man doing the ſame thing; Lampooning not only me, but alſo the very Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions uſed in the Service and Ceremonies of the holy Sacrament of Baptiſm, which the Church hath ſo ſolemnly injoyn'd; and with vil'e impudence put it in print, vainly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely giving the Appellation of God-Father to a wooden Image, and Printing, as ſpeaking of the Image St. <hi>Michael,</hi> calls it Mr. <hi>Shermans</hi> God-ſon: And remembring your Suſpectedly Superſtitious bowing at the other Sacrament alſo: Nay then, quoth I to my ſelf, theſe are but vain and ſuſpectedly ſuperſtitious, Ridiculing, Lampooning Parſons, and they would have a Bull or Grant to Lampoon and Ridicule others in Print, and in the Pulpits too; and meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon occaſion of a rotten Image, but they would not be Lampoon'd or Ridicul'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; which made me early the next Monday morning take my pen in hand, and draw all this in as much Ridicule and Lampoon faſhion as the Guts of a Superannuated Church-War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den could Invent, and therefore you were as good ſpare the Preſs, and ſpare the Pulpits for better uſes, than to Lampoon or Ridicule the Laity; eſpecially me, elſe I'le Lampoon you again and again: Say you are glad I don't Bamboo you; for truly, truly, if Divines do theſe raſcally tricks, we Lay-men cannot ſtand ſtill and let you ſpit in our Faces your venomous Malice from the Pulpit, and not wipe it off with a printed Paper, and let the World know that whatever you print or Preach againſt me, it is all but only upon occaſion, becauſe I did not defend an Image, and ſo you do but publiſh your ſelves to the world to be Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates for Images.</p>
            <p>Let me alone, and mind your own buſineſs of teaching Folks the way to Heaven, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe ſide-winds of Reflection out of the Pulpit, which makes the people remember to repeat nothing of the Sermom to one another but this: I think the Parſon paid off Mr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> to day, for Lampooning of <hi>Miniſters</hi> and their <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> But truly another replyes, they give Mr. <hi>Sherman</hi> juſt Cauſe, and he will certainly do it the more, becauſe Miniſters print Apparitions; and I'le warrant you he'l pay them all off in print again, for he is taught by the Parſon to ſay, <hi>Where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you give the people heavenly matter to talk on, Lampooning of <hi>Miniſters</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45777:4"/>their <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> and ſo you vent private Spleen in that Holy place where you ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Oracles of God: Don't tell me any more of <hi>Ludere cum Sanctis;</hi> for I will anſwer, the Devil rebukes ſin. I'le believe Benefit by the Church-prayers; bur none by Sermons of ſuch Preachers, till they leave of their Railing.</p>
            <p>If my Book, called <hi>The Birth and Burning,</hi> &amp;c. be Falſe and Libellous on the Pariſh, as you would have the World believe, why doth not ſome Body proſecute me for it: as you have hinted in your firſt Pamphlet, that it ſhould not preclude the Veſtry from further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt me; and your laſt ſayes it ſhould be taken into further conſideration: Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Folks live long: I only here add to what I ſaid in my laſt about this Head of proſecuting me, I laugh at all thoſe that talk of proſecuting for a vile abominable Image, which you call your <hi>Ornament</hi> to the Ten Commandments: O rare <hi>Ornament,</hi> a great Carved, Gilded Image, deſcribed fully in all its Demenſions by my laſt Book; a ſilly Tool of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; it had one end of a Lath tack't to its Bumfidle, and the other end to the Window, for its better preſervation from falling, leaſt the Cats ſcampering over it in the heat of their Woeing,
<q>
                  <l>Should have made it a Tumble-down-<hi>Dick,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inſtead of a Gilded and Carved <hi>St. Mick:</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>O Rara-ſhow, a moſt beautiful Bit for the Parſon to rail in Print and Pulpit, againſt him that ſaved the Pariſh a Score of Billets, by burning it in Veſtry, inſtead of Billet and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole; as to your laſt Aſperſion in your Sham-Indictment, brought in there as an Advertiſement, I do poſitively deny, that the Printed Book called <hi>Birth and Burning of this image,</hi> &amp;c. was ever read in Veſtry when I was preſent; or that ever there hath been any Veſtry ſince the Book was Printed and Publiſhed, which was but about the Twenty-ſixth of <hi>May</hi> laſt: it is true, that when my Narrative was in Manuſcript, about Four Weeks before it was printed, it was read in Veſtry, and ſome would needs cavil at it, and asked if I would own it? I told them I would, and ſaid it was true, and asked, What one Material thing was falſe? I would juſtifie it to be true; no Body gave Inſtances of any Particulars that were falſe: pray name any Material one, if you can; and will the Pamphlet ſay, I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ld make little or no Reply? Is Truth a little thing? I do tell thee, <hi>Johnathan,</hi> that the ſubſtance of that <hi>Book, Birth and Burning,</hi> &amp;c. is as true, as any thing thou ever ſaidſt or wrote of thy own making. There might he falſe Spellings, falſe <hi>Latin,</hi> and ſome Words miſplaced in the written Narrative; But what does that concern the World? The World knows nothing, but what is publiſhed in Print, and the Title is not called <hi>A Copy of a Narrative,</hi> But <hi>the ſubſtance of a Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, lately given in to the Veſtry,</hi> &amp;c. So that all that the World is to take notice of, is Firſt, Whether this Book ſince in was printed, was read in Veſtry: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Whether this Book be anſwerable to its Title, <hi>viz.</hi> The ſubſtance of the aforeſaid Narrative. Thirdly and Laſtly, whether the ſubſtance of that Book be true or falſe.</p>
            <p>And now not to enumerate all over again; I will only Repeat the moſt Material Heads, or Subſtance; Which take thus:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In 1675. we ſet up Organs: And we ſet this Image upon our Altar: which was made in 1659. by Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> who ſet it on the Steeple; till about 1675. or 1676. and then it was removed to the Altar by Mr. <hi>Clements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That this Image was made and removed without any Order of Veſtry, particularly directing the making or removing his Image.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That 1677. we beautified our Organs: As it ſtands written there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Made 1675. Beautified 1677.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That Mr. <hi>Tho. Whitebread</hi> gave us in 1677. a rich Carpet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with ſuch an Imbroyder'd Glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with a Croſs, and this Inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as in the Margent.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That this Giſt ſtands Regiſtred in a Table in our Veſtry, in the ſame Words as I mention in my ſaid Book, <hi>Page</hi> 8.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That our Linnen Cloath uſed to hang down to the Ground (or very near it) in our front, till we had this Carpet.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That ſince we had this Carpet, we expoſe that to view; and Fold upon the fore-part of the Table our Linnen.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That by the Act of Uniformity it may be allowable enough for our Communion Table to ſtand further off, yea in the middle of the Church, and ſo it would not look ſo like an Altar, as now it does ſtanding cloſe to the Commandments, with Ends <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the Furniture of the Church and Altar.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:45777:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Now for your Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. That until about 1678. we had all our Services ſaid in the Desk, and no where elſe.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That until about 1678. our Sermon did conclude in the Pulpit, with ſome Prayer or other, and the <hi>Benediction</hi> was until then ever given in the Pulpit.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That ſince 1677. you have begun and continued to read Second Service at the Altar, and at your approach to the Altar, you make a reverend low Bow towards the Altar, or Image, or Carpet.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That ſince 1677. you conclude the Sermon without Prayer and Bleſſing; and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan ſtrikes up a Tune to divert the People till you go into Veſtry, to put on the Surplice, and then you come out ſo habited, mount the ſteps, enter the Rails, make a low bow towards the middle of the Altar, then you turn to the <hi>North</hi> end, kneel and ſay ſome Prayers there, then pronounce the Bleſſing at the Altar, which ever till about 1678. was pronounced in the Pulpit.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That you, nor no Miniſter before you did ever in our Church, bow at the Altar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Michael</hi> was ſet there, (except when the Bread and Wine was there on Sacrament Dayes) for I will allow that, That you and Doctor <hi>Lafield</hi> did Bow on Sacrament Dayes at the Altar: but that was (becauſe or) when there was Bread and Wine there, and this you did, and Doctor <hi>Lafield</hi> too, before any St. <hi>Michael</hi> was ſet there: (But it was only on Sacrament Dayes.)</p>
            <p n="14">14. That you are charged to be the firſt Man that bowed there after St. <hi>Michael</hi> was up (when there was no Communion) and the firſt Man that went and Offered up Prayers and Benedictions under St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s Noſe at the Altar, where in ſome parts of the Church, People can't hear, nor ſee the Parſon; and ſo Prayers in <hi>Latin,</hi> or an unknown <hi>Tongue,</hi> may do as much good as Prayers which we can't hear.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That you were the promoter of the beginning of theſe Ceremonies, though Doctor <hi>Lafield</hi> did perſwade againſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whereas a Lecturer ought to have followed rather than led in any New performances.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That the ſuſpicion of Superſtition, and the ground of all this Noiſe, did ariſe from your <hi>beginning theſe Ceremonies but juſt about the time the Papiſts Lords were ſending to the Tower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. That you account Mr. <hi>Whitebread</hi>'s glorious Carpet a better Ornament than the Linnen which the Act of Uniformity enjoyns, for if it be not better, you are fools for uſing it; for, if we do not uſe the very beſt of every thing, other Pariſhes may be more ſerious and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly Devout than this of <hi>All-Saints-Barking,</hi> if we have nothing elſe to boaſt of, but that we have a better Carpet, and more Ceremonies, and a more Ceremonious Lecturer than other Pariſhes.</p>
            <p>And now Mr. <hi>Saunders,</hi> not to give you too great a Task at once, though there are many more obſervable Matters in my Book called <hi>Birth and Burning,</hi> &amp;c. which are true alſo; yet, I have ſingled you out theſe ſeventeen Heads, as part of the Matter charged to be the occaſion of this Indictment: it lyes on your part, to name thoſe twenty Men, that dare ſay to my Face, that theſe Heads <hi>are rude, ſcurrilous, and inſolent, or dare Aſſert, there are many Falſities and Prevarications in them; and that theſe highly tend to the diſhonour of the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Religion; and that it is a Libel upon the whole Pariſh:</hi> Except you don't mean on my part, but your own part: Nay, have you confidence enough your ſelf, <hi>In verbo ſacerdotis,</hi> to ſay, the ſubſtance of theſe Matters are falſe: If you dare not print, that all theſe ſeventeen Heads <hi>(in verbo ſacerdotis)</hi> are falſe; then let the World believe them all to be true.</p>
            <p>Nay, Mr. <hi>Saunders,</hi> ſince you have printed ſuch a ſcandalous Report of my Book, called <hi>Birth and Burning,</hi> &amp;c. you muſt give me a Reply: My Book called <hi>Birth and Burning,</hi> &amp;c. hath my own Name to it, <hi>Folio</hi> 14. and I own it all even to the End; and I put my Name to this, and own it alſo; therefore I will not take any Anſwer from any Body but you; and ſigned with your hand, that you will own; and if you Anſwer ſhort, I will call upon you for poſitive, not evaſive Anſwer: The World will judge by my Print and your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, who Writes cleareſt to the Matter: I will not accept of any Anſwer of <hi>Nath. Thom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> that is his Anſwer to the other <hi>Mercury;</hi> let them ſquabble one with the other, till they can agree, one in ſtaring the Queſtions right, the other in Anſwering:</p>
            <p>I reſpect Mr. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> becauſe he Prints the <hi>Loyal Intelligence;</hi> and the good Loyal Man, thinking the Church is concern'd, takes her part; he means well in that: He tells you the Indictment was Quaſht, for Inſufficiency of the Indictment; he don't ſay, it was Quaſht for inſufficiency of the Law of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth: Are not many Men <hi>Non</hi>-Suited, though
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45777:5"/>they have the Law on their ſide; yea, ſometimes upon a very Bond, meerly for the inſufficiency of a Declaration: and don't the very Words he quotes ſignifie as much, <hi>quaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitur per curam pro inſufficientia inde</hi> &amp;c. And he, that Loyal Man quotes Mr. <hi>Weſtcoat,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Clements</hi> for Proofs of what I don't deny, nor Object: He ſaith it was the Common practice of Doctor <hi>Lafield</hi> and Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> alſo, to bow towards the Communion-Table, when they had occaſion to go up unto it; yea, but they never had or did take any occaſion to go up to read Service on Sundayes, but on Communion-dayes; and ſo I ſay now again in this Book alſo, that they never did Bow there before St. <hi>Michael</hi> was ſet there (but on Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion-dayes,) and ſo my uſual Charge runs throughout my Book (except on Communion-dayes;) and if the exception be any where omitted, I hereby declare it ought ſo to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: But this Loyal Man does not offer a Word of Proof, that this Carved Image, was any Ornament to the Commandments, or that the Commandments, eſpecially the Second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment is a Farthing the worſe, or the Pariſh a Farthing the poorer for my burning it; nor doth any Body take occaſion of bawling for loſs of it, ſo much as a Lecturer; but it is true, that the Pariſh is two or three Pounds the worſe by Mr. <hi>Ben. Edwards.</hi> expending ſo much Money out of the Poors Stock, for making this uſeleſs <hi>Image;</hi> for the Pariſh hath no Stock, but what is intended by the Benefactors for the Poor: or ſome uſeful things for the Church; I hope future Church-Wardens will imploy Peoples Benevolence to Feed and Cloath the Poor; and not to buy Carved Images, which will not be uſeful in Churches, till <hi>Popery</hi> come in, which God prevent; I do my part to prevent it, by Writing againſt Images; I have drawn my Pen, and I will throw away the Scabbord. But I won't ſay any more to Mr. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> my buſineſs is with you, and it will leſſen the eſteem of your own Learning, to ſet a Hackney (though never ſo Loyal) to Anſwer me; you muſt take a little more pains than a ſheet of Paper, to Anſwer the great Labour and pains I have taken in my Firſt, and Second Part of my Book, called <hi>The Birth and Burning of St.</hi> Michael: I have given you a great deal of time already, ſince you firſt knew the Subſtance charged on you; and I hear you are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to conſult your Oracle, that right Loyal Gentleman, Mr. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp;c. I am content you ſhould conſult many more: lay your Heads cloſe, and lets ſee the product of that Cabal, come out in your Name; bravely fixed to it, as you did to your beloved Book, called <hi>Fiery Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition;</hi> and then if it be good and fully ſatisfactory to the World; it ſhall ſatisfie me, and every other part of both my Books, as well as any of theſe Articles which you leave unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ought to be underſtood by the World, as true, if you do not Anſwer them: For a bare ſaying, the Rubrick directs, won't do, except you name the Act of Uniformity, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you do name the place therein where it directs it ſo; and that it does as much direct, in Manner, Time, and Place, every part of your practice, as abſolutely and as well in all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Churches, as in Cathedrals and Chappels; not only on Communion-dayes, or Holy-dayes, but every Sunday, though there be no Communion; and this you are to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer under my firſt Quaere, which you will find tender'd to you by and by.</p>
            <p>If you do not Anſwer particularly to each Head, whether thoſe ſeventeen particulars be true, every ones Tongue will be calling on you, and I crave the World to credit me till you Anſwer fairly and ſully with your own hand. If theſe ſeventeen Heads be falſe, then my Book <hi>Birth and Burning,</hi> &amp;c. is falſe: But if theſe ſeventeen Heads, being the conſiderable and moſt material part of my ſaid Book, are true in ſubſtance, then now falſe is that Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Author of that Libel called <hi>The Sham-Indictment Quaſht?</hi> and who will believe him in Print or Pulpit, that would by a Pamphlet, with a Sham Title, and no Authors Name, call that falſe which in it ſelf is true in ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Saunders,</hi> I expect Anſwer under your own hand, not generally, except you own them all, but particular, which you confeſs, and which you deny, and ſhew me the Error if you can find it.</p>
            <p>And then you muſt Anſwer theſe four Queries.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether the Act of Uniformity does as much and as poſitively command the uſe of all thoſe Ceremonies, (in the ſame manner and place and times as you practiſe) as it doth all other Services therein injoyned, and prove it by quoting of places; elſe if it be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, why did you Preſs it, eſpecially at ſuch a juncture of time as 78. when the Popiſh Plot was diſcovering; O the Time, the Time the critical minite.</p>
            <p>And have a care your Anſwer do not reflect upon above a hundred Pariſhes in and about <hi>London,</hi> yea, upon our own Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi>'s Pariſh of <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> and upon about eight thouſand other Pariſhes in <hi>England,</hi> where it is not ſo uſed: For if you be in the right, then <hi>Alderſgate</hi> as well as the reſt are all in the wrong, and conſequently <hi>Alderſgate</hi> as well
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45777:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>as the Eight Thouſand muſt all go up to the Altar, and there ſay the proper Prayer; <hi>We have all erred and ſtrayed from thy wayes like loſt Sheep;</hi> and then it they be Civil, they muſt all turn about to you, and ſay, We are all taught of thee, <hi>Our moſt cringingly devout, and unſeriouſly Ceremonious, Brother</hi> Johnathan: which I dare ſay, thou won't live to ſee all <hi>England</hi> learn the Law at thy Mouth:</p>
            <p>If thy Ceremonious practices be not all abſolutely ſo enjoin'd, why doeſt thou defend them, and daily ſnarl at them that won't take thy Word for it, rather than an Act of Parliament? Tell me not of Canons, except ſuch as are allowed by Acts of Parliament; for I know no Cannons but the great Guns on <hi>Tower-hill;</hi> (and they are almoſt all worne off or gone too) except they have paſſed the Tripple Scrutiny of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo become Laws.</p>
            <p>For my part I am clearly of and for the Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is now eſtabliſhed by Law; (and O, would to God we could all be of that one uniform Opinion and Practice that is thereby eſtabliſht.) The Cerrificates which I annually make upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord (of my taking the Sacrament) on account of the Office I hold in this Honourable City, may ſatisfie the Inquiſitors in that point; but I further ſay, our Religion as now eſtabliſht, is the beſt in the World; I write not only my Judgment, but my own Experience of the <hi>Lutheran,</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Religion; the Practice and Doctrine of all which I have Perſonally ſeen, known, and underſtood, in <hi>Denmark, Swedeland, Sprutia, Germany, Polonia</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> and other parts: I value my Experiences in Religion more than my Reading; and on that Aſſurance and Satisfaction , I declare our eſtabliſht Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to be the beſt of the World.</p>
            <p>But as there is danger on one Hand, from thoſe that fall ſhort of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that it may tend to Confuſion, ſo there is danger alſo on the other Hand from thoſe that go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond; for ſuch Winged Seraphim-ſons of the Church as fly higher in their Ceremonies than his Majeſties Act of Uniformity directs, when thoſe Soarers are once upon the Wing of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe or deſign of preferment, and have got beyond or above the Kings Law, they may fly as high as the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> nay, to <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, and there Rant, and Roar, and Sing, and Curſe and Damn, and Drink, and Drink, and Drink on, till they ſpew and reel, and thruſt their Thumb under their Girdle, and loll their Head to the Larboard, and ſtrut and ſtare, and ſtagger and ſwagger, and ſo vent, and gulp up their words ſtutteringly and ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meringly, calling all <hi>Phanaticks</hi> (perhaps <hi>Hereticks</hi> too) that don't (becauſe they ought not) or perhaps can not fly as high as ſuch lofty Sons of the Church do, until at laſt near Eight Thouſand honeſt ſober Clergy-men, right bred-Sons of the Church, more Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly exemplary, and Zealous and Serious, and more regularly devout, ſhall be all ſpewed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by ſuch <hi>Mounta Seigniora</hi>'s; from home, <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing it is certainly true that there are about Eight Thouſand parochial Churches in <hi>England,</hi> where the Miniſters don't ſay ſecond Service at Communion-Table, nor don't ſay any part of the Communion Service at Communion-Table, at any time but only on Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion-dayes, or ſome perhaps upon High Holy-dayes, nor thoſe Eight Thouſand don't quit their Pulpits without Prayer or Bleſſing, to perform their after Sermon-Prayer and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction at the Altar; ought we not therefore to be ſo charitable as to believe that the Eight Thouſand underſtand their Duty and Conſcience, and that they practiſe as much as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be their Duty? And now that I may apply my Anſwer to your laſt Sham Pamphlet fully and home to you, I will invert your laſt Paragraph therein, and ſend it packing again home to you, to be imbraced in your own boſom; and ſo I ſay in your own words or ſence, <hi>viz.</hi> I leave it to all Impartial Men to determin whether the practice of above Eight Thouſand ſober and pious Clergy-men, all of <hi>unbroken,</hi> yea and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndrunken</hi> Reputation too, are to be believed and imitated, or the Aſſertion and Practice of one ſingle Mr. <hi>Saunders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Mr. <hi>Johnathan</hi> Confute and Convert theſe 8000. <hi>Et eris mihi Magnus</hi> Appollo; or elſe hang your Harp upon the Willows; for there are Eight Thouſand ſober Men, won't Dance after your Pipe; don't obſtinately run Counter to Eight Thouſand of your own Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; but either leave off your fooliſh conceited ſingularity; or elſe write Learnedly, ſo as may confute them all by proofs, which you muſt quote out of the Act of Conformity; but I will vouch there is not one word therein, nor in the Old or New Teſtament, that directs the faying Service at 2 <hi>Barking</hi> Church differing from Eight Thouſand other Pariſhes in the ſame Land.</p>
            <p>I ſay you muſt do it by Proofs, for elſe of all men no body will believe you, when you only ſay <hi>in verbo Sacerdotis</hi> (without better proof) for you are in print for Printing an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth againſt a Record it ſelf. Therefore pray quote all the places that you have for your proofs in Vindication of your Ceremonies which you uſe: If you have Authority, ſhew it,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45777:6"/>what place or page it is in, and in what Book; that ſo you may Receive Anſwer from ſome Learned hand, when the Quondam Church-Warden can anſwer you no further. But ſeeing you have firſt brought me upon the Stage, and firſt began with me by two Pamphlets, Challenging and charging me for not defending a vile Image no better; and upon thoſe two Challenges when my Vindication came forth in a Book called <hi>Birth and Burning,</hi> &amp;c. then by a late Libel entituled <hi>The Sham-Indictment Quaſht;</hi> you ſeem to challenge me again, and being once more met by you upon the Stage in print, now I do here challenge and charge you, that you have been the Beginner of ſuch Ceremonies as have been the occaſion of all this pother and noiſe about this Image; you ſmelt it would come home to your door at laſt, and therefore you firſt skreamed out; But what is the matter now? have you catcht a <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar?</hi> O! Now I have got you here, I will keep you on the Stage untill you Anſwer me, and give an account of your Faith in thoſe Ceremonies, that have made this embroyl; and I challenge and require you to anſwer me in Print with your own hand; not with a Nameleſs print, or ſome Sham or feigned Apparitions any more; for I will not lay down the Cudgells, but Bang you on the Stage in print till you have Anſwer'd a Quondam Church-Warden in Matters of your own Element: let the World ſee how you can defend your ſelf at your own Weapon by fair play (not by Railing, for all Clergy-men will yield the buckles to thee, that thou art better at that than any of them all;) come fairly, confeſs or deny Article by Article; for all your railing will but make the World ſay, O! this is becauſe Mr. <hi>Sherman</hi> pulled down an Image that Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> thus vents his Sham Pamphleted Spleen one after the other.</p>
            <p>I am not inquiring what are the Ceremonies that are to be uſed in performance of Divine Service at Cathedrals and Chappels, but what ought to be the uſe in Parochial Churches, where are eight thouſand Clergy-Men (a rank higher than Lecturers) and yet we find a Lecturer as it were, ſaying, <hi>I am more holy than all you eight thouſand are:</hi> For in his Pamphlet titled, <hi>Fiery Apparition ſeen on ſeveral days about</hi> Tower-hill, <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 3. he vauntingly boaſteth in theſe very words; <hi>Every ſober man will allow the Liberty of ſaying this, when he may know that there is not a more ſerious and regularly devout Pariſh in the City pf</hi> London, <hi>than this of</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowes Barking <hi>is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a pretty kind of a ſide-wind Reflection upon all the other Pariſhes in <hi>London;</hi> and may you not receive a Reply thus: That all ſober men will allow the Liberty of ſaying this, that there is not a more Ceremonious and unferious Lecturer in all <hi>London,</hi> than this Mr. <hi>Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> that Ridicules the Name of Godfather, and Prints ſo many Pamphlets in defence of a vile Image ſet upon the Commandments of God.</p>
            <p>Will you be ſo ſawcy as to uſe Cathedral Service in the Pariſhes of <hi>Barking</hi> and <hi>Sandon,</hi> which are pittiful ſucking Pariſhes in compariſon of Mother Cathedrals. If you have a mind to be a Cathedral fellow, muſt you make every poor man of <hi>Sandon</hi> a Cathedral fellow too: Nay then Cathedrals and Parochial Churches ſhall be hail fellow well met, and Biſhops, Deans, Prebends, Doctors, Parſons and Lecturers too: No, keep your diſtance, you are a great way off from Lawn Sleeves; for though we can all Huzza together, both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Lecturer and Pariſhioners, yet you Mr. Lecturer muſt not climb up to the top of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral preſently.</p>
            <p n="2">2. My ſecond Quaere demands Anſwer for your own ſuſpitiouſly Superſtitious Bowing at the Altar, when there is no Communion, no Bread and Wine there; who you then bow unto? becauſe it is by ſome ſuſpected a Superſtitious bowing to that Image; upon this Ground, becauſe you never went up to bow at the Altar, or ſay ſecond Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before St. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> was ſet there (except on Sacrament-dayes:) you muſt tell the World Learnedly who you bow unto, when there is no Communion, and a Reaſon why our preſent Vicar never Bows at all; ſure you won't alledge Doctor <hi>Lafield</hi>'s bowing (before St. <hi>Michael</hi> was ſet there) though only at Sacrament Dayes, as a ſufficient Argument for your doing it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an Old Man did ſo, whoſe Reaſons for bowing are dead with him; and ſeeing our living Vicar don't bow; it hath given the Prints occaſion to ſay, that Men of leaſt Learning are for moſt Ceremonies. If you can't, or don't tell the World in Print why you bow, and who you bow unto, then inſtead of ſaying (as you ought) We know what we Worſhip, the words of our Bleſſed Saviour, will be turn'd upon you; <hi>Ye Worſhip ye know not what,</hi> Joh. 4.22.</p>
            <p>O give no occaſion for People to ſay to the Lecturer of <hi>Barking,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did to the Men of <hi>Athens, I perceive that in all things you are too Superſtitious;</hi> and leaſt by your bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in an ignorant and unknown Devotion to the Altar at <hi>Barking,</hi> men be tempted to think that you ignorantly worſhip an Altar, like that at <hi>Athens,</hi> which had an Inſcription, <hi>To the unknown God,</hi> Acts 17.22, 23.</p>
            <p n="3">3. My third Quaere demands Anſwer for your Bowing even on Communion-dayes; what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45777:6"/>can you ſay in defence of your bowing at the Altar, on Sacrament dayes? and under this third Quaere, I ſhall not uſe the preſent Vicar Doctor <hi>Hicks,</hi> his not bowing for an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt you; I hope you will not pretend the ſame Reaſon that <hi>Papiſts</hi> give for their bowing; there is no Corporal Preſence (as they falſly alledge) to pay our Adoration unto, but only the Altar, the Elements, Bread and Wine; which being bowed unto, is a more ridiculous Foppery, than at moſt the very <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves are guilty of.</p>
            <p n="4">4. My fourth Quaere demands that in further Anſwer to my firſt Quaere, you ſhould ſubjoyn this, and ſay whether the Act of Uuniformity does alſo poſitively command , direct or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join the Miniſters quitting the Pulpit without Prayer or Bleſſing, and ſo ſtop that part of the Service of God; and diverting the People with a Tune of the Organ, till you can go into Veſtry, and Accouter your ſelf, to ſay after Sermon, Service or Prayers and Benedictions at the Altar, whereby many looſe the benefit of the Benediction; becauſe when the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter comes out of the Pulpit, they go out of the Church, believing all is done, not being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to it elſewhere: For thoſe that do talk of reading Communion Service at the Altar after Sermon, underſtand it only on Communion dayes, and to Communicants only; whereas your practice is direct contrary; for you go every Sunday (except Communion-dayes) out of the Pulpit to read part of the Commmunion Service to all the Congregation that remain, though there is no Communion at all: Nay, when it is Communion day, then you do diſmiſs the Congregation with Prayer and Ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing in the Pulpit; and afterwards read Communion Service at the Altar to the Communicants only; there are ſome hold theſe after Sermon Services ſhould be ſaid in the Desk; if you fall out among your ſelves, don't blame Diſſenters till you can all agree.</p>
            <p>I do grant, that when Two Miniſters are at Church, then as ſoon as one hath done Sermon, the other goes to the Altar, to ſay Prayers and Benedictions, which alſo is ſuch a kind of changing of hands, and of ſaying our Services, as we were never uſed to until the damnable Helliſh <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot was breaking out: And thus the Time, the Time, the nicking and timing of it ſo luckily, does make ſome ſuſpition ſtick.</p>
            <p>I did not think of theſe things ſo Much before, as now I do, when I ſee you bawling at me thus in print for Burning one filthy Image; and to find you skulk under diſguiſed Titles of <hi>Apparitions</hi> and Shams, as one that would fain keep Images; but Times, thanks be to God, are not ſo far gone towards <hi>Popery,</hi> as to give you confidence enough to put your Name to all your Prints; though you did begin with your own Name in <hi>The Fiery Apparition,</hi> which I lay up in <hi>pia M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moria,</hi> for my <hi>Quondam</hi> Friend <hi>Johnathan;</hi> and write upon it, This is the Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for <hi>Images,</hi> with all your Books and Texts Repeated in this Book, ſo laudably ſuitable to the occaſion; O why have you made this pother and noiſe? are you not aſhamed to call it a poor innocent Figure; and in another place St. <hi>Michael;</hi> and in <hi>Thomſon,</hi> to call it a Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole? <hi>And thus this Tool,</hi>—<hi>Is Chriſtned by every Fool.</hi> O ye <hi>ſounding Braſs and tinckling Cim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. &amp; <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Does not your many Pamphlets make you like him in <hi>Judges</hi> 18. &amp; 24. who bellowing for his Idols, being askt what ailed him, cryed out; <hi>You have taken away my gods; and do you ask, what ails me;</hi> don't imitate this Mans fooliſh Idolatrous zeal any longer, but rather go cool your ſelf at <hi>Sandon;</hi> and then come calmly as a Miniſter ſhould do, and admoniſh me in private, for not defending your Images no better.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Johnathan,</hi> I can't leave Retorting not only your own Texts, but a Sentence of your own upon you, taken out of your own dear Book Tituled, <hi>A New Narrative of a Fiery Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſeen on ſeveral Dayes about</hi> Tower-hill, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Your words are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know how unhandſom it is to interrupt Men of Buſineſs, with little particular concerns of our own,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But becauſe you confeſs it unhandſom, I ſhan't chide you ſo much as I would, having whipt you ſo much already for the fault, that I am afraid you will cry, <hi>O Sir, I will never diſturb Men of buſineſs more:</hi> be ſure you don't then, no otherwiſe than barely Anſwer all my ſeventeen Heads, and other four Quaeries; and ply that work, and do it quickly, and put your Name to it; and then I'le ſay, thou art my Good Son of the Church: have a care, and do your work well, for I have the better ſide; you are to maintain the Doctrine of Images well, which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> hold; elſe you'l loſe as much ground on their ſide, as you have done in ſome ſober Mens Judgment on the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s ſide.</p>
            <p>Men won't like Images, becauſe thoſe Dark innocent Creatures will put us to the charge of Candles firſt; and when the Candles have ſtood ſo long unlighted, as St. <hi>Michael</hi> did on the Altar, we ſhall have ſome Body Preach on this Text, <hi>The Blind lead the Blind,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo tell us from thence, 'tis time to light our Candles at the Altar, that the Eyes of our Images
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45777:7"/>being ſo enlightned, by ſuch blinking Candle-light pretended zeal, may ſee to do good to the blind Folks that ſet one <hi>up</hi> on the Steeple; and that removed it <hi>up</hi> to the Altar, and that Print it <hi>up</hi> in ſome Pamphlets that they are aſhamed to own; and that Preach it <hi>up</hi> in Pulpits by a New Lectorian way of reflecting upon a Church-Warden that pulled it down; rendring it to Vulgar underſtandings Sacriledge.</p>
            <p>After we have once got Images and Candles, we may then be perſwaded by ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerious Lecturer to begin a ſuſpected Superſtitious Adoration, upon a pretence that the Image hath wrought a Miracle in making him Conſcientious of his duty; and in opening the eyes of his underſtanding, enabling him to know the Rubrick, and execute the Act of Conformity better than he had done for many Years ſince his Majeſties happy Reſtauration, whom God long preſerve; which this Lecturer never could ſo underſtand to be his Duty, as to practiſe it, before the Altar was Adorned with this Image, and the glorious Carpet of Mr. <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread,</hi> nor ever could bring his lofty Heart to Bow there, before this great Carved, Guilded Image of the all powerful and victoriouſly Thiumphant St. <hi>Michael</hi> was ſet there (except on Sacrament dayes when Bread and Wine was there.)</p>
            <p>If you will conſult Holy Writ, you ſhall find who they were that were ſome of the firſt that thought Images fit companions for the Ark or Church of God; why, it was a parcel of lewd <hi>Philiſtian</hi> Prieſts and Diviners and Conjurers, as you may read the Story at large in the firſt Book of <hi>Sam.</hi> c. 6. v. 2. <hi>And the</hi> Philiſtians <hi>called for the Prieſts and the Diviners, ſaying, What ſhall we do to the Ark of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>They ſaid,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Send it not empty,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Ye ſhall make Images of your Emrods, and Images of your Mice,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Theſe were laid in the Cart with the Ark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were <hi>Philiſtian</hi> Prieſts and Diviners, that begun but with ſmall Mice, but now we are called Prieſts and Divines, we muſt have them a Size bigger, a luſty Fellow as big as our St. <hi>Michael;</hi> yea, and he muſt ſtand fifteen or ſixten Years ſeaſoning on the Steeple, for fear he ſhould ſtink, before he be thought ſweet enough to ſtand on our Altar; perhaps you may ſay, though the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> thought to ſtop the God of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Mouth in thoſe dayes with an Image as big as a Mouſe, yet the ſame God now muſt have one as big as a Man. I further obſerve, that theſe Images being ſent away with the Ark in a Cart, drawn by Two Milch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kine that were tied to the Cart, yet theſe ſenſleſs Beaſts did not prize (becauſe they knew not) the worth of what they had in Poſſeſſion (<hi>viz.</hi> the Ark of God) but went on lowing as they went, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. meerly for the want of their Calves, which were ſhut up at home, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Well, what if theſe Two <hi>Philiſtin</hi> Cowes did ſo, muſt we have two Milch-kine at <hi>Barking</hi> do ſo too? though they have the Ark of God (the Church) in their poſſeſſion; nay, though they are tied to it as it were with a Girdle, by their Order of Prieſthood; yea, though the Ark of God (the Church of <hi>England</hi>) be (thanks be to God) tied to them alſo by an eſtabliſhed Law of the Land; yet O Heavens bleſs us, what ail ye, that ſome Body lately went on lowing as they went in their Preaching (if reading can be ſo called) for the loſs of one ſilly Bulkin; as if the Ark of God were taken from you! who is about to do it? I know no dainger the Church of <hi>England</hi> is in (nor the Government thereof, as it is now eſtabliſht by Law) by burning a great Carved, Guilded Image.</p>
            <p>You have the Ark ſtill, or rather the Ark has you; for you are much about the middle of it (as near as the Pulpit can ſtand) when you are going on lowing thus for the loſs of a Calf: What meaneth the bleating of theſe Cattel; O ye fooliſh and unwiſe, to go on lowing at ſuch a ſilly rate, murmurring in obſcure Expreſſions at him that ſhut up your Calf at home, and wrapt it up ſo warm in the Veſtry Chimny: pray mind your buſineſs, take care of the Ark, the Church of God, that you are tied to; carry that to its place; For our Church as now eſtabliſht by Law, needs no <hi>Images</hi> for her Companions, whatever <hi>Papiſt</hi> Prieſts, and <hi>Philiſtin</hi> Diviners may think.</p>
            <p>Men will but make ſport, and ſit and laugh at you, as I do; if you go on lowing at ſuch a rate, and cry, Hark, Hark, How one of theſe Milch-kine go on lowing for a Calf; thanks be to God, theſe curſt Cowes or Bulls, have ſhort Horns, elſe I ſhould be in great pain and peril of Bull-goring; as for ſuch Men as talk in the Pulpit of a Woe to them by whom of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences come, and Sacrelidge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who do they apply it to, in this caſe? I ask them ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, whether my placing this Image for an Ornament in our Veſtry Chimny, were greater Sacreledge than his Act, that took it from the Steeple to adorn the Commandments therewith? I ask whether the Chimny were not the warmeſt place, and more proper than the Commandments, which do ſo forbid Images, that Images are an obomination?</p>
            <p>The Chimny as well as the Commandments, were both places contrary to the deſign of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45777:7"/>its firſt creator or maker, <hi>viz. Ben. Edwards,</hi> who made it and placed it on the Dial, for a <hi>Tom</hi> Tell Clock: And yet I believe honeſt <hi>Ben.</hi> may like the Burner better than the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mover, or Pulpit Bawler, or <hi>Apparition</hi> Pamphleteer; becauſe my Burning had ended all the Noiſe, if the Publiteer had not been a Pamphleteer, and ſpread it in Print: Leave off for ſhame thoſe Gloſſes in the Pulpit about Sacriledge, for every one thinks it too much, being on no other occaſion but a vile Image: If you don't, it will ſhortly be ſaid by Folks, Come let's go to <hi>Barking</hi> Church, to hear the Parſon rail againſt the Church-warden that burnt St. <hi>Michael;</hi> and every Country Parſon that comes to Preach at <hi>Barking,</hi> won't think he have made a Sermon ſuitable to the place, if he han't talkt of Sacriledge, or reflected upon him that pull'd down St. <hi>Michael,</hi> till at laſt Men will come and look in at Door, and turn again, ſaying, O are you there with your Sacriledge about a rotten Image.</p>
            <p>Like him that Preached ſo often upon the Text, about the two She-Bears, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 24. in every Church he came at; one paſſing by, looked in, and hearing him, ſaid, O are you there with your Bears? and ſo went out of the Church again. It would become Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers much better to lead ſuch ſober lives, as might convince the World that they are <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Temperance;</hi> but I will not come too near the Ark, leſt I ſhould touch it; for if I do, I muſt expect <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi>'s fate, as far as is in a Lecturers power, though I believe I may prove it Lawful for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> being a <hi>Levite</hi> to touch the Ark: But I anſwer, it is as Lawful for me to Anſwer your Prints, as it was for you to begin to print againſt me; whether it were Lawful or nor for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> to touch the Ark, is not my buſineſs now to treat upon; elſe I could ſay ſomething to it, for he being an Officer of the Ark, as a <hi>Levite</hi> might think himſelf concerned to ſupport the Ark when he perceived it in danger.</p>
            <p>So in our preſent caſe, when an Image had given ſuch offence and ſcandal by ſtanding in ſuch a place, and your going up to read Service at the place where it ſtood, which you never did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Image was ſet there (except on Sacrament dayes when Bread and Wine was there;) And alſo an Indictment being brought againſt the Church-wardens for letting it continue; ſure then it was lawful enough for ſuch an Officer as a Church-warden to pull it down and Burn it; eſpecially at ſuch a juncture of time as when the Ark, the Church of God was, and is, in ſo great danger of falling into the hands of the <hi>(Philiſtians) Papiſts:</hi> and Images are ſuch inſeparable Badges of that Religion, that there is no <hi>Papiſts</hi> Church that I ever ſaw (and I have ſeen many) without them.</p>
            <p>And who ever blames me in Print or Pulpit for Burning this abominable Badge of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, they cannot diſtinguiſh themſelves from being pleaders for Images; and they that plead for Images in Churches, are as near a-kin to Superſtition, as Superſttion it ſelf is of kin to <hi>Popery;</hi> and whoever Bows to an Image, or Fathers ſuch Texts, as are in the Firſt and Laſt of the Three Pamphlets <hi>upon the occaſion,</hi> can never quit themſelves from a Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious leaning towards Superſtition; and he that Bows to meer Bread and Wine, that juſt came out of a ſawcy Clarks hands before the Miniſter hath laid his Conſecrating hands, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Words of Conſecration; muſt needs give <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves occaſion to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach thoſe that do ſo, more than we can Reproach them for Bowing after Conſecration.</p>
            <p>I confeſs I can't write of ſuch practices without emotion; for I love not to treat ſtarcht nonſenſical Folly with too much Gravity; there is no Man hath a more due Reſpect to pious and ſerious Clergy-men, than my ſelf; but to ſee Miniſters that ſhould imploy themſelves in Inſtructing us from Gods ſacred word, ſpend their time in ſcribling Libels in defence of odious Images, who can behold theſe things without Indignation?</p>
            <p>I am verily perſwaded, that I do upon this occaſion diſcharge my Duty to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> to detect all Image loving, and cringingly Ceremonious and unſerious Lecturers; eſpecially if all this may tend to drive this one out-lving Dear home to his Park at <hi>Sandon,</hi> to take care of his Flock in the hands of a Hireling; for how ſhould that Flock yield Milk that have neither Paſtor nor Paſture; for, when you are ſo often and ſo long near them, at <hi>Chelmsford,</hi> you give them ſcarce above one or two Sermons in twelve Months laſt paſt: Sure the Lord Biſhop, as well as <hi>Barking</hi> Pariſh will take notice that you harbour and loyter at <hi>Chelmsford,</hi> and not at <hi>Sandon,</hi> though you pretend to go to <hi>Sandon,</hi> when you leave <hi>London;</hi> but when the People of <hi>Sandon</hi> ſee themſelves thus ſlighted, at laſt they will Sue you for <hi>Non</hi>-Reſidence; why do we complain of Diſſenters, when <hi>Non</hi>-Reſidence is a kind of <hi>Non</hi>-Conformity to the Law in the Clergy, an a great cauſe of it in the Laity? For Sheep will go aſtray where there is no Shepherd:</p>
            <p>Now for this, thou art inexcuſable, O Man, ſo much to neglect thy Duty and Conſcience at <hi>Sandon,</hi> and yet, in the mean time to keep ſuch a Noiſe here at <hi>Barking,</hi> about reading <hi>Second Service</hi> at Communion-Table; and leaving our Pulpit without Prayer or Bleſſing; and in Loyal <hi>Nath. Themſon's Loya<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Intelligence,</hi> Numb. 27. doſt cauſe to be Printed as a Reaſon for you reading Second Service, Thus <hi>The Lecturer indeed was Conſcientiouſly deſirous to obſerve the Rubrick which commands the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come cloſer to you: if you would have the World believe that the Rubrick directs it, and you are ſo <hi>Conſcientiouſly deſirous to obſerve it,</hi> why then do you not cauſe your <hi>own Curat</hi> to obſerve and do the ſame every Sunday? As you have brought that way up here, why do you not Conſcientiouſly take care it be ſo done at <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> where you are ſo far abſolute, that it is in your own power? And if out Curate will not do it, you may get ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if you can, that will: Therefore no Body will believe you Act <hi>Conſcientiouſly</hi> in the matter at <hi>Barking,</hi> when you do not cauſe the ſame to be done at <hi>Sandon</hi> every Sunday as you have brought it up to be done here at <hi>London:</hi> For your Curat reads Second Service at <hi>Saydon</hi> in the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k, though you read Second Service your ſelf as the Altar at <hi>Sandon,</hi> whoſe few times you preach there.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:45777:8"/>But for your after Sermon Service of going up to the Altar and giving the Benediction there, though you practiſe it at <hi>Barking,</hi> yet when you are your ſelf at <hi>Sandon,</hi> you your ſelf do not do ſo there; it ſeems you have <hi>Two ſorts of Service for God Almighty,</hi> a <hi>City Service,</hi> and a <hi>Country Service;</hi> as if our God were a God of the Hills, but not of the Valleys, for this way of after-Sermon-Service, neither you nor your Curate do practiſe at <hi>Sandon;</hi> for at <hi>Saydon,</hi> not only the Curate conſtantly, but you your ſelf alſo when you Preach there, do diſmiſs the people with Prayer and Benediction from the Pulpit, without going up to the Altar after Sermon: perhaps it is becauſe you have no Organs to Dance you up to the Altar, nor Carved Image, nor no ſuch rich Carpet at <hi>Sandon,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in your Conſcience you ought not to ſay all ſuch rich Service there as you do at <hi>London:</hi> But you muſt give the World a better Reaſon than your <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which in twenty five Miles varies as much as the Compaſs does in ſome Latitudes, or as the Sun in ſome parts of the World is hotter than in other parts.</p>
            <p>But that Learned worthy Man you Curate hath a very good Character, for Life as well as Doctrine and knows his duty as well as you; and I hear he never bows at the Altar at <hi>Sandon,</hi> it may be he is Conſcientious in not bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor doing the Altar Services, to avoid offence, becauſe it ſeems there hath been great buſtle and oppoſition to theſe Altar-ſervices there, the rather becauſe they were inforc't by you at <hi>Sandon</hi> alſo, but about 78. or about the time of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot, though you had been in that Living ſome Years before.</p>
            <p>One would think you might eaſily read a few more Sermons to your own Pariſh, ſince it is ſo eaſily done to read a Book in the Pulpit; it is no ſuch doughty accompliſhment, for ſeven, or eight Years Study at the Univerſity, to come and read a Sermon; and it is ſtrange, that ſuch Readers ſhould get Living upon Living, only becauſe they can read a Buſineſs: Though it is true many a Man ſaves his Life by Reading, when the Ordinary reports <hi>Legit ut Clerious,</hi> or if you will, He Reads <hi>like a Clegy-man;</hi> is it not a ſhame while other Arts, are every Day ſo much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, to ſee Doctors, Parſons, and Lecturers ſtand ſtill, or rather dwindle back to Readers? which is very unlike the practice of our Bleſſed Lord and his Apoſtles, who never Read either their own or other Mens Works, but their Heads and Hearts were full of the Matter, Doctrine, and Inſtruction that they had to ſay.</p>
            <p>Indeed our Bleſſed Redeemer himſelf, in one place, and at one time, called for a <hi>Book,</hi> but as ſoon as he had read the Text, cloſed the Book again, and gave it to the Mininſter, or a kind of Deacon among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and then went on Preaching.</p>
            <p>But where a Preacher ſhall ſtudy and premeditate how to vent his Spleen handſomly againſt his Pariſhioners, and then read it out of a Book, wherein it was written with a Pen dipt in Gaul, inſtead of common Ink, will any Body think he (that does ſo) ſpeaks by the <hi>Spirit of God?</hi> or is this becoming the Gravity of ſo Sacred a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, for Doctors, Parſons, and Lecturers to become Readers, Readers?</p>
            <p>Eccleſaſtical Hiſtory tells us, that the Emperor <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate was once a Reader in the Church, no great honour for him or the Church to have ſuch a Reader; and I read in later Hiſtory that in great praiſe of one of the <hi>Henrys,</hi> was ſtyled <hi>Bean-Clerk,</hi> becauſe he could Write and Read.</p>
            <p>It ſeems that in <hi>Julians</hi> dayes a Scholar was <hi>Rara avis;</hi> but in theſe dayes when Learning is ſo common and ſo much advanced, is it not a ſaid ſight to fee Doctors, Parſons, and Lecturers to be but Readers in the Pulpit, and to have their Heads and Hearts ſo little affected with what they have to ſay? that if they chance to turn over two or three Leaves too much, they are at a great loſs, and with a world of Hums and Haes before they can get in again, which looks like A, B, C; nay, take away their Books and Notes, and they can ſay nothing at all; or no better than ſome ſuch plain Men as Coblers of ſome other Trade: Which brings to mind the Anſwer of a <hi>Reading Preacher</hi> (if it be not <hi>Contradictio in adjectio</hi>) an honeſt and unfurniſht Head, one that haunted Taverns more than Study; who having read a Sermon of excellent Compoſure, and being askt how he got ſo good a Sermon with ſo little Study; replyed it was all his own, for he bought it for Six Pence in <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard, and it was Six Pence the beſt laid out of any thing he ever did in his life, (and he was a <hi>Lecturer</hi> too) for he had Twenty Shillings for every Lecture Sermon, and at a ſeveral Church it was as good as at firſt, <hi>freſh and new;</hi> and he read it every time better than other; theſe are your brave Pulpit reading DONS of the BOOK.</p>
            <p>Is it not ſomewhat ſtrange, that in the Pulpit the ſame Man would be called a Preacher, becauſe he reads out of a Book! and in the Desk the ſame Man is ſaid to be a Reader, becauſe he reads out of a Book, I would not have toucht ſo much in the Preſs upon Reading Miniſters, if they did not ſome of them aim at me (meerly upon an occaſion of my Burning an Image) in touching ſo much in the Pulpit and Preſs upon Sacriledge; a word you muſt not uſe this Six Months in our Pulpit, leſt People think the Burning of this Image broyl's in the Parſons Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach ſtill; and the more Reflections Men make (either from Preſs or Pulpit) on a defacer of Images, will but render ſuch Men ſuſpectedly <hi>Superſtitious, Lovers of Images,</hi> therefore leave off your Scribling in defence of an Image, and come to the grand Matter, and write Learndedly in Anſwer to my ſeventeen Heads, and four Queries.</p>
            <p>I don't ſee, <hi>Jonathan,</hi> how thou canſt Anſwer my Queries, and aſſert the Direction of the <hi>Rubrick,</hi> ſo as clearly to make it out that there is any Law that abſolutely and poſitively enjoyns every part of thy practice at Altar-Services; Nay, thou canſt not tamper and endeavour to do it to any purpoſe, but thou muſt ſeem to Act the part of him that is called an Accuſer of the Brethren; thou muſt reflect, if not directly accuſe about Eight Thouſand of thy Brethren, yea and thy R. R. F. alſo; which will ſtick in their Stomachs, and they will all Print againſt you; and it will be ſuch a ſcandal for ever upon thee, as a thing that even Father <hi>Whitebread, Cum mult is aliis.</hi> of that <hi>Crucian</hi> black Crew choſe rather to <hi>Truſs</hi> than to accuſe their unholy Father, or any of their Brethen, and if you rightly conſider their couragious Example, thou wert better do juſt ſo too, <hi>(Truſs)</hi> rather than beray thy own Neſt; conſider the unſeaſonableneſs of urging Doctrines of Ceremonies, upon ſo <hi>Laudable</hi> occaſion as an <hi>Image;</hi> and at ſuch a juncture, when we fear the prevailing of a Religion, that is compoſed of Ceremonies and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>And Conſider the rather with your ſelf who firſt put you upon running into theſe Ceremonies; I have good ground to believe the Report of ſome of the People in and about <hi>Sandon,</hi> that it was a Lay Gentleman, who in ſome former Years had been himſelf or ſome of his Relations of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion; and therefore conſider and think it no wonder, if that Gentleman preſs hard upon you for a ſtrict Obſervation and a due Performance of a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Ceremonies; becauſe he may perhaps think that God's worſhip in the Church of <hi>England</hi> conſiſts as much in Ceremonies, as it did ſo in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; but I hope you have not ſo learned Chriſt: And then you will be able to reply to that Gentleman this other Text, <hi>viz. God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him Muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> Joh. 4.24. And pray Study, Preach and Practiſe this your own ſelf, and begin, nor continue no new Ceremonies (at leaſt let your betters go before you,) I mean ſee it done at <hi>Alderſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> before you Print up the Legality of it at <hi>Barking</hi> or <hi>Sandon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it ſeems you have made Diviſions at <hi>Sandon</hi> alſo, and a Noiſe about the Country, as well as die City; meerly by your ſingularity, and Ceremonious practices, to the wonder of ſome Neighbouring Learned Clergy-men about <hi>Sandon.</hi> What will you diſturb City and Country, and with the heat of your pretended Conſcientious
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45777:8"/>zeal boyl all the goodneſs out of the Meat (Religion) into the Broth of Ceremonies? Nay, if the marrow and goodneſs of Religion, and quinteſſence of it be gone into the broth, and the All of it lyes there; then it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you contend ſo much for the Broth that Religion is boyl'd in; I mean the Broth of uninjoyn'd Ceremonies: for I would not be thought to Ridicule any Ceremonies that are injoyned by the Law: it is you Mr. Lecturer that imbroyl <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Sandon,</hi> and by your bowing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> occaſioned an Indictment at <hi>London,</hi> and then that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned three Pamphlets at <hi>London;</hi> and this my Second Vindication alſo, it was <hi>thoſe Lecturers, Lecturers,</hi> that in Pulpit and Preſs did turn the World up-ſide down in 41. in 41. and for a Lecturer now in theſe times to Print up more Ceremonies and Bowings than the Law hath enjoyned, tends to turn us quite topſie turvy, becauſe it may tend to bringing in a Religion that is Compoſed of and upheld by Ceremonies, from ſuch Religion, <hi>good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I read what the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Woman ſaid, <hi>Our Fathers worſhipped in this Mountain, and ye ſay, that at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is the place where Men ought to worſhip,</hi> John 4.20.</p>
            <p>So may I ſay, we had all our Morning Services, both Firſt and Second Services all ſaid in the Desk at <hi>Barking,</hi> ever ſince the Creation of the Kings Act of Conformity till about 78. and now you <hi>Johnathan</hi> ſay that the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar is the place where the Men of <hi>Barking</hi> ought to worſhip the ſame God, by ſaying ſecond Service there.</p>
            <p>So I alſo may ſay, that ever ſince the Creation of the ſaid Act, our Sermons did end with ſome Prayer and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions in the Pulpit until about 78.</p>
            <p>But now you <hi>Johnathan</hi> ſay that the Men of <hi>Barking</hi> ought to receive the benefit of your after Sermon-prayers and Benedictions at the Altar (after you have bowed to it) and not from the Pulpit.</p>
            <p>It will be now expected that you, that have thus expoſed your ſelf not only in Loyal Mr. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> but in your own Three ſingle Sheets, and have expoſed me alſo to the World, when you had no juſt occaſion <hi>(except in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of an Image.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay it will now be expected that you ſhould give the World a Learned and Good Account in Print of the whole Matter particularly, why your Conſcience is ſtreighter Laced at <hi>London,</hi> than it is at <hi>Sandon,</hi> or elſe (Life, Doctrine, Print, Pulpit Reading, Ceremonious Bowing, Critical time, lucky Minit, and all Circumſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) you will come on, and go off the Printed State under a Charactor and in the wildeſt Notion of the largeſt ſized Latitudinarian of any Clergy-man in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In your Book of <hi>Fiery Apparition,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Page</hi> 4. you have theſe words, <hi>I could have wiſhed with all my Heart, that the thing had made no Noiſe abroad;</hi> I believe by this time you do wiſh ſo with all your Heart, and Head, and Soul alſo; thou wiſheſt it had made no Noiſe, and yet you begin the Noiſe your ſelf with Two Pamphlets, before ever I Printed one word.</p>
            <p>I find in the ſecond Book, <hi>Page</hi> 4. more of your own Words being thus, <hi>And I very well underſtand that Liberty of Conſcience, and Liberty of the Preſs, are things that have an unhappy Influence upon the whole Nation; and therefore as I am no Friend (in the preſent wild Notion) to the one, ſo I ſhould hardly have been guilty of uſing the other, had there not been this Too juſt occaſion for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Juſt ſo I invert this Sentance of your own. If Clergy-men will take Liberty of Conſcience in the Pulpit and Preſs to inveigh againſt me; why then I can't forbear being Guilty of uſing the Preſs, to tell the World how you Ring of Sacrelidge about one vile Image: And I ſhould never have Printed, <hi>had there not been this too juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for it,</hi> which are alſo your own words. Pray God the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion and Church as it is now eſtabliſht by Law, never receive a greater Bow in <hi>England,</hi> than my Burning an Image: God Almighty, who equally hates Superſtition and Sedition, blaſt the deſigns of all thoſe on either hand that tend to ſeek the Deſtruction of this true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church of <hi>England</hi> (as it is now eſtabliſht by Law) <hi>eſpecially thoſe of her own Houſhould,</hi> for I am an enemy to all that go beyond (as well as to thoſe that come ſhort) of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> For every ſtep beyond, if it be a Superſtitious ſtep, it may ſooneſt of all be a <hi>Popiſh</hi> ſtep, the rather becauſe at this day, <hi>Romes</hi> Agents are ſo ready to take Men by the Hand and Dance them into <hi>Romes</hi> Fopperies, with the pleaſant Song of welcome <hi>John Sanderſon,</hi> welcome, welcome.</p>
            <p>And then I will ſay, farwel <hi>John Sanderſon,</hi> farwel, farewel.</p>
            <p>I kept theſe Two Aſtoniſhments till at laſt in hopes I ſhould have ſeen you rectifying your miſtakes in Print, one is your Text, <hi>Where no Law is, there is no Tranſgreſſion:</hi> Muſt you be taught by a Church-warden that there is a Law, (except you are agreed with ſome <hi>Papiſt</hi> who leave that Commandment out of their Deacalogue?) you will one day find it in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.3, 4. in theſe words, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any Graven Image, nor the likeneſs of any thing that is in Heaven above, or in the Earth beneath, or the Waters under the Earth, thou ſhalt not Bow down to them, nor worſhip them,</hi> &amp;c. Though you evade this Image, by calling it a Figure, or Symbol, yet you may one Day be told this was the <hi>likeneſs</hi> of ſomething in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus you bring down upon your own Head, the Thunder of the Holy Pen-Man in theſe Words, <hi>Her Prophets are light and treacherous Perſons: her Prieſts have polluted the Sanctuary,</hi> THEY HAVE DONE VIOLENCE TO THE LAW, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.4. This might ſtrike you Dead and Dumb, but that you have quoted a Text for your ſhelter in the end of the next <hi>Verſe,</hi> THE UN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JUST KNOWETH NO SHAME.</p>
            <p>But I wonder the leſs at you, ſeeing you are grown ſo dairingly Impudent, as to add one Chapter more to God's Book than ever God made, which is my ſecond Aſtoniſhment, <hi>viz.</hi> in your Sham Indictment quaſht, you end with a Text which you ſay is in <hi>Zeph.</hi> 4.5. whereas there is but Three Chapters in <hi>Zeph.</hi> that ever any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Miniſter could find, however the words you may treaſure up to your own ſelf, which are theſe, <hi>The unjuſt knoweth no ſhame;</hi> being ſuitably proper to you that of meer Malice, and without any Provocation by me given you, or without ever before or ſince ſpeaking one word friendly to me about it, or inquiring whether things were ſo or no, yet you have premeditatedly and falſly repreſented the Matter of firſt Seſſions, as I have laid open in my firſt Book, which the Reader muſt peruſe as well as this Second Part, elſe the whole Matter will not be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; thus when Lecturers venture to Print things they hear in a Tavern, or Alchouſe, or Coffe-houſe, how do they ſham themſelves? and how great a Fire does a little ſpark kindle, when a Lecturer hath the kindling? O theſe Seditious Lecturers made the Fire blaze deviliſhly, when they had the blowing of it in 41.</p>
            <p>Now I have waded through a Two Years troubleſom Office, it muſt ſtir up heat in a Stone, to ſee an unſerious Lecturer concern himſelf to reflect upon me in Print: but what I have ſaid might make this READING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON OF THE BOOK bluſh if he had any ſhame.</p>
            <p>But what new fangled Company doeſt thou keep, that hath taught thee to ſtretch and hale and pull Gods Book out a whole Chapter longer than it was made, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an may perceive thou art one won't ſhrink, but rather run out in the wetting: for no Body will think thou kept's ſuch a drie Gizzard long, as to believe thou wert drie at Heart when you wrote it: But it may prove at laſt of good uſe, and ſerve for the beſt Anſwer you can think of; for though you can't plead <hi>Non eſt factum</hi> (at leaſt a privity to all Three Pamphlets) yet you may plead, <hi>Non compos
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45777:9"/>Mantis,</hi> or ſome ſuch other Plea as may bring you within benefit of the Clergy; and for you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo much as<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> remember what Room, or what Company, no, nor ſo much as what Tavern you were in when any of thoſe Three Pamphlets were wrote; and ſo drop the Cudgels, and let the Liquor run through the Stage one way, and the Lecturer off another way: and ſo for this time end all our grumbling with this merry Jig, while You and I ſing the Tune thus, UNTIL YOU ANSWER IN PRINT.</p>
            <q>
               <l>This Dance it will no farther go,</l>
               <l>Pray good Sir, why ſay you ſo?</l>
               <l>Becauſe the Parſon won't come too;</l>
               <l>He muſt come too, and he ſhall come too, whether he will or no.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Elſe all, all the World will point at you, and ſing, <hi>Farewel</hi> John Sanderſon, <hi>farewel, farwel.</hi> And you will be hiſs'd at by every Porter of <hi>London,</hi> and piſt at by every Boy of <hi>Sandon;</hi> they wil ſay there goes the ſilence Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; not ſilenced by his Biſhop, but by his <hi>Quoudam</hi> Church-warden.</p>
            <p>You muſt excuſe me from running ſo much upon Ridicule, for if <hi>I</hi> did not do ſo (upon occaſion of an Image) all that know me, would not think it my own. But let the Reader Obſerve, I did not begin with the Lecturer, but he with me; I do but defend my ſelf from being Pope <hi>Gregorv's</hi> Aſs: and which is worſe from being Prieſt-rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: nor I don't, condemn Pope <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Opinion, that by Oxen were meant the Clergy: ſo let it be with his <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Clergy; I only Comment upon his Unholineſs's Opinion: and ſay that Oxen are Creatures not of Gods making; for God made only (Male and Female) Cowes and Bulls, but Oxen are only the Manufacture of ſome cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sow-Gelder: But Lecturers ſure muſt have been ſome buſie Factious Canundrum invention, <hi>ab Origine,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were thought ſo Seditious in 41.41. And may not we ſay of them, Parſons we know, and Vicars we know, but who are ye? Perhaps you will anſwer, as in <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.23. <hi>We are thoſe that tythe Mint, Anniſe, and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min;</hi> (which give me leave to call uninjoin'd Ceremonies) <hi>and have omitted the weightier matters of the Law:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray the Reader further to obſerve, that I intend not to Ridicule any thing that the Law directs; for I really preſs Comformity to the Law, but when I find Pulpits as well as Prints vent Vanity and Froth; I can't forbear giving you a <hi>Trantrum</hi> or two.</p>
            <p>Preach no more againſt them that ſcoff at thy Miniſters; for I ſcoff at none but thoſe that Print falſe Pamphlets, and rail in the Pulpit, only upon occaſion of a ſilly <hi>Image:</hi> And it cannot be thought a ſuitable Anſwer to you, if I do not blow off your Froth with a little bluſtring and ſeeming vanity of my own; and ſo I add this one <hi>pania Brochia</hi> more:
<q>
                  <l>Why, talk now no more of <hi>Ludere cum Sanctis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor Bow to no Saint, but the goodly St. <hi>Francis;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then Diſciples you'l have to dance to your Lure;</l>
                  <l>But I Bulkin at <hi>Barking</hi> who can indure?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now according to our Lectorian new up-ſtart way of writing Pamphlets, to begin with one Text and end with another, which I am afraid is an Old trick Reviv'd from 41.41. but to ſhew I am an apt Scholar, I'le give you two for one.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>YE WORSHIP YE KNOW NOT WHAT, <bibl>
                     <hi>John</hi> 4. 22.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>AND IF THE BLIND LEAD THE BLIND, BOTH SHALL FALL INTO THE DITCH, <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.14.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>And ſo once more you are bid farewel, farewel, by him whom you have Thrice Pamphleted <hi>EDM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ND SHERMAN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>I Have Penned my Matter as it occurr'd to my Memory, I hope the honeſt Reader will excuſe ſome Tautolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and not having made every Paragraph hang ſo ſuitably together as I might have done: Confider I am but a Lay-Man; I declare again, that none of the Drolling part is intended againſt any thing injoyned by Law, but only to Droll at the Singularity of a Lecturers new Practices of Ceremonies, not uſed by himſelf for about Sixteen Years after the Act of Uniformly was made, and now enlightned by a pretended Conſcience at <hi>London,</hi> and yet contradicted by his own practice at <hi>Sandon;</hi> therefore let my Drolling part ſhift for it ſelf; and it will be Commendably done if the Lecturer can without Drolling or Rayling anſwer more Learnedly and fully Satisfactory to the World: which he can never do, except he</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt gathers up the Streſs of every thing I have urged and charged upon him as well in my firſt Book, as in this Second Part alſo, relating to the Altar Services both before and after Sermon; and his Bowing juſt at the Altar and no place elſe in the Church: And he muſt prove our Communion-Table ſtands as it ought by Law to do; and, whether we can hear or not, yet he is bound to ſay thoſe Services juſt there where it is.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He muſt give a Reaſon why he never ſaid theſe Second Services, and after Sermon-Services at the Altar, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Michael</hi> was ſet there; and prove this Image an Ornament to the Commandments, and my Burning it Sacriledge: elſe why is all this Noiſe?</p>
               <p n="3">3. He can't anſwer any thing to the purpoſe until he hath reconciled the Practice of the Lecturer of <hi>Barking,</hi> to the practice of the Parſon of <hi>Sandon,</hi> that the World may know which of them is the <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> or <hi>Non-conformiſt:</hi> At him <hi>Johnathan</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> too him <hi>Saunders</hi> of <hi>Barking,</hi> and when you two have agreed, then too him all ye Eight Thouſand, at them (ſtoutly) ſingle Mr. <hi>Saunders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Though Prayers may be better heard from the Desk or Body of the Church, yet you muſt affirm, that they cannot be legally performed except at the Altar; but have a care your Aſſertions don't contradict the Act of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and your Practice thwart both.</p>
               <p>The Reader may Obſerve that I do poſitively limit the Begining of theſe Altar Services to about <hi>An.</hi> 78. though not ſo exactly to the very Day the Lords went to the <hi>Tower;</hi> I would have no Reflections caſt on the Pariſh of <hi>Barking,</hi> nor on Clergy-men in general, but particularly ſuch as come to our Pulpit and Reflect about this Image: Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> hath ſingled me out, and now I ſingle out Mr. <hi>Saunders:</hi> I will juſtifie my Burning this Image, let him juſtifie his Printing againſt me for Burning it; and his Altar-Services and Bowings which occaſioned the Indictment and Noiſe: I deſire the World to leave us a free Stage, and that no Body would intermeddle, but let us Two Print out the Matter, with our own Names Subſcribed.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> does Bow, and ſo differs from Eight Thouſand Clergy-men in <hi>England,</hi> by his Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it will be well for him, if he gets himſelf to be one of the Number of the Seven Thouſand that had not Bowed to the Image of <hi>Baal,</hi> which I read of in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.4. But then he muſt tell the World in Print, who he Bows unto, and why he Bows at all, and in that Place only; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elſe Men will turn upon him the Texts before quoted,
<q>Ye worſhip ye know not what.</q>
                  <q>I perceive that in all things, you are too Superſtitions.</q>
               </p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed the 10. of <hi>June,</hi> 1681. for Mr. <hi>Sherman</hi> the Author:</p>
            <p>And Publiſhed by <hi>Richard Janeway,</hi> in <hi>Queens-Head-Alley in Pater-noſter row.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
